hello everybody and welcome to part 1 in
大家好，欢迎来到GMOD LUA教程的
the gmod lua tutorials now in this
第一部分，在这期视频里
video we're not gonna be doing any
我们不会进行任何
coding we're just gonna be going over
代码操作。我们只是粗略地过一遍
the basics of what client and set-aside
客户端和服务端的基础概念
is because they're two very important
因为这些概念非常重要
things to know before you you actually
你最好在实际为GMOD
start coding for Garry's Mod now even if
编写代码之前就了解它们
you want a code in single-player it's
哪怕你只是写单人模式的代码
still vital you know this information
这对你来说也是很重要的
because believe it or not there is still
因为，不管你信不信
a client and a server relationship when
哪怕在单人模式下
you're in a single-player game so we'll
仍然有一个客户端-服务端关系
go ahead and I'll open up Photoshop and
所以让我们继续讲正题吧，等我一会儿打开Photoshop
try my best to explain this so imagine
我会尽力解释
that this here so the way how server and
现在发挥一下你的想象力
client are represented with orange and
服务器和客户端分别用橙色
blue so this circle here this is the
和蓝色表示，这个圈圈代表服务器
server ok now the server is what handles
而服务器会处理
pretty much every every aspect of
游戏运行的各方面的信息
gameplay in a server such as when a
例如
player should die dealing damage to a
一个玩家应当死亡、或者对其他玩家造成伤害
player update in all of the other
更新其他客户端的
clients on changes and stuff along this
有关信息的更改，这些都是在这条
line so this is us ok we are this circle
连线上发生的。OK我们客户端就是下方的
down here and here is our link to the
这个圆圈，这是我们与服务端的连接
server now us as the clients can't do
此前已经提到，客户端并不能做太多
much in terms of controlling the game as
控制整个游戏进程的事情
like I said it's already it's the server
是服务器在控制
that controls now multiple clients can
许多的客户端
be connected to the same server and
连接在同一个服务端上
let's say
好现在
you let's go ahead and just quickly
这是你....哦还是让我先赶快
finish my amazing drawing now this is me
把我这美妙的绘画完成，现在这个圈就是我
okay this one here now I move slightly
对就是这里这个圈，现在我开始慢慢
left so on my screen I move a little
向左移动，我的屏幕上显示我向左移动了一点点
left then information is carried across
然后我移动的这个信息通过连接
this connection to the server the server
传输到服务端。接着服务端
handles this information moves my player
处理信息，然后在服务端的世界里
in the service world and then the server
移动玩家，然后服务器
then goes and updates everybody else on
向其他玩家更新
my new position where I move to now with
我移向的新位置的信息
certain things that can only be done on
某些事件只能在
the server and there are certain things
服务端处理，还有些事件只需要
that can only be done on the client okay
在客户端处理即可
now there is a little bit in the middle
剩下的那些中间部分
called shared which is where things can
叫做"共享事件" 这些事件
be done on both client and server but
需要同时在客户端和服务端处理
mainly you're going to be working in
不过你的程序的主要工作
server to do the majority of the logic
是在服务端处理这些逻辑问题
of your programs now when we first up
接下来我们将进行起步的工作
we're going to be starting in the client
我们现在先从客户端开始
and writing some basic client-side
并编写一些简单的客户端脚本
scripts and once we start to get the
一旦我们掌握了
gist of that but I'm going to move over
客户端的内容，我们就将进一步学习
into the server and once we start to
有关服务端的内容。接着
understand how the server works we're
如果我们理解了服务端的运行机制
then going to go ahead and we are going
我们就会继续学习
to work on both of them so we'll find
客户端和服务端同时处理的工作
out how to communicate between those
最终我们通过你的脚本实现
with your scripts
服务端与客户端的交互
and how to make something that works
以及做出一些功能来实现
with both people such as say you wanted
与玩家间的交互，例如你想
to send a message from this player over
从某一名玩家处发送一条消息
to this player how could we do that in lua
发往另一位玩家处。我们如何在LUA内实现呢？
and things along that line so I
以及沿着玩家间这条线的其他功能
know this video was short it's just the
我知道这条视频很简略，这只是
basic introductory of you know we're
一个基础的导入环节，目的是让你知道
going to be going now I do want to also
我们将要做什么。我现在还想提醒一下
say that if you have not already seen my
如果你还没有看过我的
Lua tutorial series and you're not
LUA教程并且你也
familiar with Lua at all I recommend you
完全不熟悉LUA的话，我推荐你
watch that series there will be a link
去收看那个系列，链接会附在
in the description if you have finished
简介中。如果你已经了解这些了得慌
a series and you're moving on in the
你可以继续看接下来的视频了
next video we'll be getting into some
下个视频我们将会进行
coding hopefully some basic scripts but
一些代码编写，可能只是一些基础的脚本
yeah I hope you understand what I've got
但我希望你能理解我之前所说的内容
if you don't feel free to leave a
如果你还没理解，请尽情留言询问
comment and I will get back to you and
我会尽快给你解答(译者注:我也会的!)
thanks for watching see you in the next video
感谢你收看这个视频，下个视频见